A Guide to the Fauntleroy Family Letters, 1807-1848
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Fauntleroy Family Letters, 1807-1848
Library of Virginia
21293
17 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mrs. George F. Vose, Richmond, Virginia, in 1938.
Biographical Information
Samuel Griffin Fauntleroy was born 7 May 1759 in Richmond County, Virginia. He served as a militia officer during the American Revolution and was appointed a justice of King and Queen County, Virginia. Fauntleroy inherited "Farmer's Mount" through his first wife Elizabeth Payne Todd (1761-1794), whom he married 7 March 1782, and by whom he had six children. He married Sarah Lowry (1766-1840) 28 January 1796, and they had five children. He died 8 December 1826 and was buried at "Farmer's Mount."
Moore Gardner Fauntleroy, Samuel Griffin Fauntleroy, and William Todd Fauntleroy were sons of Samuel G. Fauntleroy and Elizabeth Payne Todd Fauntleroy. Moore G. Fauntleroy (2 March 1789-29 April 1858) attended the Medical College of Philadelphia, graduating in 1812. He served as an army surgeon during the War of 1812, and after the war, he practiced medicine in King and Queen County. He married Anne Catherine Roberta Latane (1798-1868), and they had eight children. He died and was buried at "Farmer's Mount." Samuel G. Fauntleroy (11 May 1791-June 1857) attended the Medical College of the University of Pennsylvania, graduating in 1814. He practiced medicine in King and Queen County. He lived at "White Marsh" which he renamed "Marialva," then at "Piedmont." He married Lucy Elizabeth Cooke (1800-1821), and they had one child. William Todd Fauntleroy (25 September 1794-February 1848) married first Lucy Ann Gwyn (1806-1829), and they had two children. He married second Elizabeth Edward Downing (d. 1876), and they had four children.
John Moore Fauntleroy (4 August 1818-4 September 1889) was the son of Moore Gardner Fauntleroy. He attended Rumford Academy in King William County, Virginia, and the College of William and Mary. He resided first at "Pine Top" in King William County, then "Beechwood" in New Kent County, Virginia. He married Ann Willis Sizer (1832-1906) 20 October 1852, and they had five children. Fauntleroy died at "Beechwood" in New Kent County. His body was reinterred next to his wife's at Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia, in 1912.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1807-1848, of the Fauntleroy family of King and Queen County, Virginia, consisting mainly of letters, 1807-1811, to and from Moore Gardner Fauntleroy, (1789-1858) of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, including letters, 1811, from his father Samuel Griffin Fauntleroy of King and Queen County, Virginia, discussing Moore Fauntleroy's medical education and its costs, news regarding the family, and information on family slaves; and letters, 1811, from his brothers William T. Fauntleroy and Samuel Griffin Fauntleroy (1791-1857), both of King and Queen County, sending local and family news, including results of a local election for the Virginia House of Delegates. Also consists of letters, 1807-1811, from William George Vidal and Catherine Vidal of Middlesex and King and Queen Counties to Moore G. Fauntleroy providing news of local events and of his family and discussing the Vidals' move from Middlesex County to King and Queen County. Also contains letter, 31 December 1809, from Moore G. Fauntleroy to his grandfather, Dr. Gardner, discussing his medical education and his attendance at various religious services in Philadelphia; and letter, 13 May 1811, from Moore G. Fauntleroy to Haige[?] Davis of Middlesex County asking him to collect on a note owed Fauntleroy and the details behind the note. Also includes letter, 24 February 1848, from H. W. L. Temple of Essex County, Virginia, to John M. Fauntleroy of King William County, Virginia, concerning religion and Fauntleroy's spiritual well-being.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Letter, 31 December 1807[?], from William George Vidal and Catherine Vidal of Middlesex County, Virginia, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, sending social and family news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 31 December 1809[?], from Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, to Anthony Gardner, King and Queen County, Virginia, discussing his medical education and commenting on different religious services he attended in Philadelphia. Also contains family news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 8 January 1811, from his father Samuel G. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, discussing Moore's medical education and its costs and sending half a $100 note. Also comments on the family and the health of slaves., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 19 January 1811, from his brother William T. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, sending local, social, and family news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 30 January 1811, from his father Samuel G. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, sending the other half of the $100 note and asking for an account of Moore's expenses. Also comments on the family and health of the slaves., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 27 March 1811, from his brother Samuel G. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, sending local, social, and family news and family news. Includes a postscript by Moore's grandfather Anthony Gardner., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 13 May 1811, from [Moore G. Fauntleroy], Philadelphia, to Haige[?] Davis, Middlesex County, asking him to collect on a note from a gentleman to whom Fauntleroy had loaned it. He adds a tale of how the gentleman had it stolen, most likely losing it gambling., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 May 1811, from his brother Samuel G. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, Philadelphia, sending social and family news, including news of the health of his father's slaves and news of the local election for the House of Delegates., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 2 July 1811, from William George Vidal, King and Queen County, to Moore G. Fauntleroy, King and Queen County, informing him of the Vidals' move from Middlesex County to King and Queen County. Also sends news of Fauntleroy's family., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 24 February 1848, from H. W. L. Temple, Essex County, Virginia, to John M. Fauntleroy, King William County, Virginia, discussing religion and the state of John's spiritual well-being., 2 leaves, negative photostats.